[Music]
medicinal plants are said to be nature's
gift to human beings to promote a
disease-free healthy life here in
reference to amla a fruit the indian
gooseberry described as an ayurvedic
wonder
you hear a lot of that larger-than-life
talk about amla coming out of indian
medical journals who can forget amla a
wonderberry in the treatment and
prevention of cancer amla is so revered
that you find serious scientists at
serious academic institutions and
serious peer-reviewed medical journals
making statements like this
every part of the indian gooseberry
plant has its unique therapeutic
characteristic for the remedy of almost
all the ailments and can be adopted to
say bold italics single bullet against
disease
okay then
i first ran across it in this famous
article looking at the total antioxidant
content of thousands of different foods
i did a series of videos about it ages
ago and to my surprise the number one
most antioxidant packed single hole food
on the planet on average was
amla dried powdered indian gooseberries
beating out the prior heavyweight
champion cloves with just for
comparison's sake up to 100 times or
more antioxidants by weight than
blueberries
so here's this fruit that has enjoyed a
hallowed position in ayurveda the
ancient system of medicine in india so
hallowed it was mythologically pegged as
the first tree in the universe
so for thousands of years before we even
knew what an antioxidant was
they were revering this plant that just
so happens to turn out to be the most
antioxidant packed fruit on the planet
earth
okay you've got my attention
but i still need to see it put to the
test
well
indigenous tribal healers used amla to
treat diabetes so researchers decided to
give it a try
this is the study that originally bowled
me over in fact the subject of one of my
first nutrition facts videos of all time
over five years ago
the effect of amla fruit on the blood
sugars and cholesterol levels of normal
subjects and type 2 diabetic patients
in my video i talked about the jaw
dropping effects of 5 cents worth of
this powdered fruit 5 pennies worth
compared to a diabetes drug
but what about the cholesterol effects
if you take healthy individuals and give
them a placebo sugar pill
nothing much happens to their
cholesterol
ideally we want our total cholesterol
under 150. this is a pretty healthy
group the average cholesterol in the u.s
is over 200
which is where the diabetic started out
in this study and when you give them
placebo pills nothing much happens
either
but give people just about a half
teaspoon of amla powder a day not some
extract or something just dried indian
gooseberries a powdered fruit and
this is what happens
that's like a 35 40 drop in three weeks
absolutely astounding that's the kind of
thing we see like you know six months
after putting people on statin drugs
what we care about most
is ldl the so-called bad cholesterol
shooting for under at least 70 ideally
no impact to the placebos but again just
about a half teaspoon of amla which
would cost about five cents a day
so like a buck 50 a month and boom
these results knocked my socks off i
mean they're just
unbelievable
that's why i was so excited after all
these years to dig back into the animal
literature to see if these findings had
been confirmed or replicated elsewhere
so i typed amla into pubmed and waded
through all the papers on using amla to
decrease methane in cow farts and speed
the growth of chickens
or hey what about amla ice cream
after all amla is packed with fiber and
phytonutrients in contrast ice cream is
not therefore
and indeed ammo incorporated into ice
cream increases the antioxidant capacity
though i would not recommend it for
cholesterol lowering
ah but here we go a comparative clinical
study of amla head to head against the
cholesterol-lowering statin drug
simvastatin sold at zocor which i'll
cover
next
[Music]